Great.
So we had some feedback and
office hours and other times
that it might be helpful
to have a high-level recap
of the algorithms that
we've talked about so far
to try to understand where some
of the pieces fit together.
So I put together one slide that
is a little bit more high level
but actually captures
almost all of the algorithms
that we've seen so far.
And in particular, we've
talked about both online
and offline algorithms, where
online refers to scenarios where
the policy will be
used to collect data.
And offline means that
we're given a data set.
And we cannot do any
additional data collection
in our environment.
And in the offline
setting, we talked
about two different
classes of reinforcement
learning methods that
use on-policy data
collection in order to improve.
We referred to the first
type as on-policy RL
and the second type
as off-policy RL,
where on-policy RL, you
can collect data but only
from the current policy.
You can only use data
And this means that you are not
going to be reusing past data.
You can't use offline
data and so forth.
And this include algorithms
REINFORCE or the vanilla policy
gradient method.
And then within the
realm of off-policy RL,
this was where we could start to
reuse data from other policies,
including data from policies
before we took a gradient step
on our policy parameters.
And this included
algorithms like PPO
and importance sampling.
And then we talked
about algorithms
that are more off-policy that
can reuse data from policies
that are even more
different and where
we use a replay buffer
to store the data
from those past policies.
And that included
algorithms like DQN and SAC.
And then I colored these
different algorithms
different colors because
the blue algorithms only
involve training a policy.
So we refer to them as
policy gradient methods.
PPO and SAC learn both
a policy and a critic.
And so we refer to them
as actor critic methods.
And there's also algorithms
that only learn a critic
and don't explicitly
learn a separate policy.
And those are often referred
to as Q-learning algorithms,
such as DQN.
I should also mention that
PPO is often actually referred
to as a policy gradient method,
although you do actually
learn a value function.
And so we typically
were referring to it
as actor critic in this
class to avoid confusion.
And then separate from these
classes of online methods,
we also have offline RL methods
that we started talking about.
And these built upon a lot of
the ideas we saw in online RL.
But I have to cope with
the fact that you're not
collecting any data at all.
And we looked at two
different approaches there.
One is to only considering
actions in the data.
And this included algorithms
like AWR, AWAC, and IQL and also
an algorithm like SQL that
implicitly is constraining you
to actions in the data
but not so explicitly.
And this is through
conservatism.
Now, for these RL algorithms,
generally, as you move right,
you need more online data.
And so that means
that typically they're
going to be more expensive
because online data is often
more expensive than offline
data because it's harder
to repeatedly collect a
large amount of online data.
And then lastly, before
we talked about RL,
we also talked about
imitation learning algorithms.
And this can also fall
within the bucket of offline
and online, although
there's a bit
different set of assumptions.
The first imitation learning
algorithm we covered
was kind of vanilla
behavior cloning, where
we're taking a data set
and trying to imitate
the actions in that data set.
And then we also talked
about an online algorithm
that is online both
in terms of the policy
and in terms of
querying an expert,
like asking an expert
what is the right action
on this new data
that I'm collecting.
And I put these in--
they're in a little bit
of a separate category
because they have
different assumptions.
You don't need a
reward function.
But you do need
pretty good data.
And you're not going to
be able to outperform
the average behavior
in your data set.
Cool.
So that's an overview including
a lot of these different terms
that we see in
reinforcement learning,
like offline, online,
off-policy, on-policy,
and so forth, and
imitation learning
versus reinforcement learning.
Cool.
So what we're going
to talk about today
is we're going to talk about
model-based reinforcement
learning.
And model-based
reinforcement learning
can actually be applied to
all of the different classes
of reinforcement learning
methods on the previous slide.
Someone has a special
place in my heart
because I used to do
actually quite a bit of work
on model-based RL.
And I think that there's a
lot of really cool things
that you can do with model-based
reinforcement learning.
We'll talk about the key idea
behind it, how to learn models,
how to use those models,
including with planning and data
generation.
And then we'll also look at one
case study in dexterous robot
manipulation.
And as a teaser for
that, the methods
that we'll be
talking about today
is we'll allow a robot to
do something like this,
which is pretty cool.
This hand has more
than 20 degrees
of freedom, more than 20
different joints that's
controlling.
And then the key
outcomes is trying
to understand how
we can learn and use
dynamics models and the
different challenges
and trade-offs with this
whole class of methods.
Cool.
So the key idea behind
model-based reinforcement
learning is
essentially we're going
to try to learn a simulator.
Can we learn how to predict
the future for actions
that we might be taking?
And for robotics and driving
and other physical systems,
this might be
modeling the physics
of some particular system
if you can directly
observe the underlying physical
entities in that system.
And alternatively,
if you can't directly
observe the different entities
in that physical system
and model them, then
this might look something
more like video prediction
conditioned on actions
that the agent wants to take.
So for example, I
might want to predict--
if I say something to someone
else, how will they react?
Or if I, for example, move
my legs in a certain way,
will I fall down?
Will I go that way?
Will I go that way.
And so forth.
In terms of what this video
production might actually
look like, we've seen pretty
cool videos coming out
of large models
like Veo 2 and Sora.
And these are examples
of videos that are
generated by a neural network.
You could imagine that
these kinds of models
could be very useful for
training systems like cars,
robots, quadrotors that are
flying through different places
in order to learn about how
their actions affect the world.
Now, models could look
something like models
of the physical world.
They could also look at
models of other things.
So for example, if you
wanted to learn a policy
to make money on
the stock market,
then one of these
simulators would
be trying to predict what
will happen to the stock
market over time and if your
actions have any effect on that.
And then if you're trying to
train an agent to play a game,
then this sort of
model will underscore
the rules of that game.
And actually, in a
lot of games, you
might actually already
know the rules of the game.
And you may not
even need to learn
a model in the first place.
For example, in chess, if
you take a particular action,
you know the outcome.
You know how the piece will
move as a result of that action.
And then it comes down to--
in two player games or three
player games or multiplayer
games, you might need
to model other players.
Modeling other players-- you
can sometimes consider that
as part of the dynamics.
But oftentimes, it's
actually modeled separately.
So you don't even
necessarily need
to consider it as part of
this simulator of the world.
And for example, you
might be able to use
your own model of yourself
as a model of another agent.
So if we can learn a
simulator, how would we use it?
So the sketch of
an algorithm would
be something like this,
where we get some data.
Then we learn a simulator
on that data that's
going to trying to
predict the future
for the present and
some action that I
might take from the present.
And then try to run
your favorite method
inside the simulator.
So for example, maybe you
have a simple scenario,
where you want to get from the
green point to the red point.
You might collect some data.
This is collected
from some policy.
Then you would train some
neural network conditioned
on a state and an action.
What is the next state?
And one way that you
could learn this is just
by minimizing the
L2 loss between
your predicted next
state and the next state
observed in the data.
And then in terms of running
your favorite RL method,
you could use one of the RL
methods that we've covered.
Or you could use
a planning method.
And we'll talk about a couple
planning methods today.
Cool.
So now, I have a
question for you.
So here's a sketch
of an algorithm.
Does anyone have thoughts
on what might go wrong
if you follow this sketch?
Yeah.
So the idea there was that
your simulator might not always
be accurate.
And so similar to what we saw
in reward modeling and also
arguably what we saw when
training Q-functions,
you might exploit
those inaccuracies.
Those inaccuracies
might compound.
And then what you've learned
in your learned simulator
might not transfer
to the real scenario
that you're trying to
learn a good policy in.
So there's also this
data coverage issue.
So similar to what
we've seen when
training Q-functions
and other things,
if this pi 0, if
this initial policy,
is different from the policy
that you're ultimately learning,
then you're going to
have this mismatch.
And you might not
have coverage--
your model might not be
accurate for the states that
are visited by the policy
that you're learning.
So this is mostly basically
what's on this slide exactly.
So if you have
some environment--
maybe you want to
navigate a maze--
then you might collect some
data set from some policy.
Maybe the policy does something
like this yellow arrow.
This is your data set.
But this data set doesn't
cover the whole maze.
And so then if you wanted to
go to this part of the maze,
for example, or this
part of the maze,
then your model probably
wouldn't be very accurate
about the mazes in those
parts of the environment.
And so then you wouldn't be able
to learn a policy for reaching
those parts of the maze.
And then for the second
point, you might not always
have an accurate simulator.
So here's an example of
a video generated by Sora
with the prompt,
a humanoid robot
standing near a table with a
red, green, and blue cubes on it
performs a cube stacking
task with red on the bottom
and blue on the top.
And you can see that the
video generation does
some creative
things with physics,
where it kind of changes
the colors of the block
and synthesizes blocks
out of thin air.
I would love for my robot to be
able to do something like this.
Seems very useful.
But this is not modeling
what robots can actually
do in reality.
And to this point,
when you're actually
trying to develop
this kind of model,
oftentimes you might
need to make choices
that are dependent
on the domain,
like if you're trying to
train a video prediction
model versus training a
model of low-level physics
with friction or training a
model of the stock market.
You might have some
choices to make
in terms of what are
the inputs to that model
and how are you
training it, what's
the architecture, and so forth.
And some domains are
going to be much easier
to simulate than others.
And then lastly,
for this last part,
even if you have a
really good simulator,
this doesn't mean that it'll
be easy to get a good policy
or to get actions that
are accurate as a result.
You still have to do the RL
process using the simulator.
And you need to account for
inaccuracies in the model
during this process.
Because usually, your
model is not perfect.
You don't have a perfect
simulator of the world.
That's the key idea
behind model-based RL.
Now, let's talk a
little briefly about
how to learn a dynamics model.
We don't have too much
time to cover this.
So we'll just talk
about it briefly.
And then we'll spend
most of the time
on how to use a dynamics model.
So in terms of learning a good
simulator or a good dynamics
model, there are some scenarios
where you might know it already.
And you could just use it.
And then you're in great shape.
There's also scenarios
where you might actually
know most of the
model, like if you
are in a simplified
robotic control setting
where you're trying to
push an object on a table.
Maybe you know most of it.
But you don't know the friction
coefficient of the table.
Or in driving, maybe you
have a pretty good model
of how the car is
going to accelerate,
how it will move forward
with a given steering command
and a gearing a given thing.
And you just need to model
some additional things.
In those cases,
you might actually
be able to leverage knowledge
that you know about the world
and then fit those unknown
parameters using the data.
This is actually, I think,
one of the cooler ways
to try to incorporate
domain-specific knowledge
into reinforcement
learning algorithms.
And then in almost all
scenarios in practice,
you don't really know the model.
And this might be because
you can't-- for example,
if you're trying to
manipulate some objects,
maybe you kind of know
roughly the laws of physics.
But you don't know
the vast majority
of how an object is going
to behave because it has
lots of different properties.
And there's many
different objects.
Or you don't know how people are
going to interact in the world.
Or other drivers are going
to behave in the world
and so forth.
And in these scenarios,
the typical practice
is to learn the
model from scratch
with a neural network or some
other function approximator.
Now, there are a couple
options here as well.
So if you are using image
observations, for example,
and you're trying to predict--
if your state space, for
example, is an image of--
I don't know.
Maybe this is like you have a.
Car and there's other cars here.
And you're trying to predict
in video where those cars will
be moving in the future.
And maybe there's, I don't
know, some trash on the ground
or something like that.
I'll refer to this
image as st. One option
is to generate
entire future video,
like the videos that we
saw on the previous slide.
This would be
conditioned on actions.
But this might be
fairly expensive to do.
Because if you have
to basically be
predicting this entire
video over time,
that's a pretty large thing.
And you have to model
all the different details
of how all of the pixels are
going to change in the future.
And so one alternative
option that is sometimes
used to learn dynamics
models is instead
of modeling in the
image space, you
could instead learn some lower
dimensional representation
and then model in that
representation space.
So you, for example,
for a given state,
you could learn
some sort of encoder
that maps this to a lower
dimensional representation
space.
Maybe we'll refer to this as zt.
And then instead of learning
a model in the original image
space, we could then try to
learn a model that predicts
future zt's, like zt plus 1.
This can be a good
alternative in scenarios
where it seems like it'll
be very expensive to learn
a full model.
It also has its own
challenges because you
need to figure out how to
get this representation
in the first place.
And if you have a good way
to get good representations,
it can be a good choice.
So the question was we are
going to be losing information
by going to a lower dimension.
And so, is the main reason
to do this in terms of cost?
Yeah, and exactly.
So the main reason
to do this is to try
to reduce some of the
computational costs associated
with this because you might
be losing information.
And the key idea
is that there is
some parts of this observation
that doesn't matter, perhaps
like the exact
texture of the road,
whether it's really dark black
or maybe a little bit worn down.
In masonries, that
might not matter.
And so if you can learn
a representation that
discards that information
that's irrelevant,
then you don't have to spend
so much compute modeling
all those details
that don't matter.
The other thing that
I'll mention here
is that oftentimes when you're
trying to learn these models,
typically with supervised
learning or generative modeling
techniques, you often will also
need to learn a reward model as
well.
And the reason for
this is that if you
want to be using your
model to generate data
or to see into the
future, you need
to see into the future
not just the states
but also how those predicted
states will lead to rewards.
And so we'll talk
about what that looks
like on the next couple slides.
The question is,
does model learning
have to happen end to end?
The way that it works is we
are optimizing for our ability
to generate future states.
And there are
actually pros and cons
that we'll talk about with
regard to that objective.
But one way to think
about it is like,
how well can I model
the distribution
of P st plus 1 given st, at.
Another way to think
about it, especially
if you have more
deterministic dynamics,
is, how well can I
minimize the error
between my predicted st plus
1 and the actual st plus 1?
So how do we go about
using a dynamics model?
The first approach
that we'll talk about
is we'll actually start
by talking about planning.
And so this is actually going
to be a little bit different
than simply running
reinforcement learning
inside your learn simulator.
And the way that
this could work is
you can think about
your MDP, where
you have your current
state that you're in.
And then you take some action.
And then this affects
your next action.
And then as a result
of that, you'll
also get some future reward.
And then this
process will repeat.
You'll take another
action that influences
the state after that, which will
yield some additional reward.
This reward might also
depend on the action
that you took as well.
Now, in some of the
past reinforcement
learning works that
we talked about,
we kind of assumed
that we didn't really
know the relationship.
We kind of don't know how the
actions affect future states.
And so we have to figure
out how to optimize rewards
without using direct gradients.
But if we can actually
predict what a future state is
and what a reward is
based off of that,
if we train a reward model
and a dynamics model,
then we could
actually just directly
backpropagate from
rewards into actions.
And so we could potentially
directly pass gradients
from your rewards
into your actions.
And what this would look
like is your objective
would be to maximize either
just the current action or maybe
the next sequence of actions
for the sum of future rewards.
Maybe we'll do this t
prime for some horizon.
So maybe we're optimizing
for rewards from time t
to time t plus H.
What this would
look specifically--
I guess we can show it
on the slides as well.
So we're trying to maximize
the sum of rewards.
And we often refer to
this kind of problem
as looking into the future is
planning a sequence of actions
that will maximize rewards.
And so if we have some model
of how we predict future states
and actions and
rewards and if we're
modeling that with
a neural network,
then we can also compute the
gradients of that neural network
to backpropagate rewards
into actions as following.
And so then, specifically,
what this would look like is--
well, first, you would
collect some data.
Then you would train your model.
Maybe that's to minimize
f of s, a minus the--
this is your
predicted next state.
This is your true next state.
And then once you
have this model,
you could then find a
set of actions that is--
actually, just to be explicit
for this optimization,
we're minimizing the
parameters of our model.
And then the third step is to
try to find a set of actions.
So this would be a hat t
to t plus H. This is like,
what is the course of actions
that will lead to good rewards?
And this would be the argmax
of the sum of rewards--
sum of t.
This is over--
Running gradient descent on
actions is a little bit--
backpropagation to
actions is a little bit
different from the typical
backprop that we look at.
So oftentimes, when
we run backprop,
we're doing it with regard to
parameters of a neural network.
Here, we're actually
backpropagating
into these actions right here.
And so specifically, what
this kind of third step
would look like is you will
need to basically initialize--
just like you randomly
initialize your neural network
parameters, you'll need to
initialize your actions.
Then you need to
compute your gradient.
So this would be the gradient of
the sum of rewards with respect
to the actions that you take.
And to compute
this gradient, you
can think of it essentially--
like if you use the chain rule,
the gradient will be the
sum of rewards with respect
to the states.
So that would just be based
off of your reward model.
Then if you apply
the chain rule,
you could then
have a second term
that's d states d
actions to actually get
the gradient of the rewards
with respect to the actions.
And then once you
have your gradient,
then you could use it
to update your actions
with gradient descent.
And so then maybe this
is your initial a hat
a hat t to t plus
H is going to be
your previous a hat minus alpha
times this gradient right here.
I'm going to put
this separately.
Yeah, great question.
Actions would be
continuous in this setting.
We'll also look at
scenarios where we can do it
with discrete actions as well.
We're assuming rewards
are deterministic.
But we've actually
always assumed
rewards are deterministic.
And you can consider any
sort of non-determinism
being encapsulated
by the dynamics
and in the state variable.
Correct, yeah.
So here, we have
a dynamics model.
And I guess I didn't
explicitly write this.
But you would also be
trading some reward function.
Maybe this is like
r psi for example.
And this would be using some of
the reward learning techniques
that we've talked about.
There's also some scenarios
where you might know the reward.
So it might be, for example,
like forward velocity if you're
trying to learn how to walk
or some distance to some goal,
that sort of thing.
And in those cases, you don't
need to learn a reward function.
So the question is, if your
dynamics model is stochastic,
how do you backprop through it?
It kind of depends on how you're
modeling the stochasticity.
So if you're using a
Gaussian, for example,
there are certain tricks for
differentiating through samples
from Gaussian, whereas if you're
using something like a diffusion
model, it would look
a bit different.
So it is kind of
model dependent.
And so far, we're talking
about deterministic models.
So the question is, will
this start to exploit errors
in the reward?
So this will start to exploit
both errors in the reward
but also errors in
the dynamics model.
So if your dynamics
model is inaccurate
or if your reward
model is inaccurate--
if either one of
them is inaccurate,
then you might get actions
that aren't actually
going to take good
actions in the world.
And that's a problem.
And so we'll talk
about that in a second.
So this is a good question.
So I guess instead
of repeating it,
I think what would
be helpful is--
we aren't actually
learning a policy here.
And that's essentially
what you're pointing out.
And this is like becoming
our "policy," quote unquote.
This is like our behavior.
Do I have a good term for this?
I guess.
I mean, yeah.
This is sort of the
"policy," in quotes.
And this is what
we call planning,
where at every
single state, we're
actually going to be planning
forward and thinking ahead.
What are the actions I
should consider that I
think will lead to good reward?
And so we'll actually be doing
this optimization process,
every single state when
we're doing planning.
So on the slide,
we're going to be
running some policy
to collect data,
learning a model to try to
be able to accurately model
the dynamics, potentially also
learning a reward function as
well.
And then we'll be
backpropagating
through the reward
and the dynamics
in order to choose actions.
And then once we
choose those actions,
we'll be then be executing these
actions in the environment.
And then after we
execute those actions,
we'll then be rerunning
this planning process again.
So in particular, I guess maybe
to explicitly write that out,
we'll have a step 4 here.
That is to actually execute
a hat t to t plus H.
And then you will then move
on back to step 3 after you've
executed these H actions.
So the question is, we're only
planning over a horizon of H.
And what if we have
an infinite horizon?
In principle, the math--
well, it's a good question.
So we'll talk a
little bit about this.
For now, we're going to be only
considering this short horizon
planning.
And in eight-ish
slides or something,
I'll talk a little
bit more about what
happens if you want to
do infinite or very long
horizon things.
And we'll also talk about some
of the shortcomings of this.
Now, so far, we talked
about gradient descent
for optimizing actions.
And this is actually
not the only way
that you can do optimization.
So it's probably the
optimization technique
that you're most familiar
with because we use it all
the time for neural networks.
But there's other ways that
we could optimize a function,
specifically when we're trying
to optimize the sum of rewards.
And if we think about
gradient-based optimization,
typically we have something that
we're trying to optimize over.
In this case, we're trying to
be optimizing over actions.
And the thing that
we're trying to optimize
is the sum of rewards maybe.
Actually, also, there's
a small mistake here.
This should be a plus sign
because we're maximizing,
not minimizing.
So the way that gradient descent
works is you kind of randomly
initialize some action,
like right here.
And then you evaluate the
gradient at that position.
So maybe you find
that the gradient
is like pointed this way.
And then you then say, OK, I
should move probably over here.
And then maybe you sample this.
You choose this action because
that's kind of a step size away.
You evaluate the gradient there.
And you find that the gradient
maybe looks something like this.
And then you say, OK,
maybe I should move further
to the left but
a little bit less
because the slope is less steep.
And then you get maybe
something that looks like this.
And you're like, OK,
the gradient is 0.
And so maybe I won't be
sampling any further actions.
And then your final choice
after running gradient descent
is this value right here.
Now, an alternative way to try
to do a kind of optimization
is instead what I'll call
sampling-based optimization.
This is also called
gradient-free optimization.
And the way that this works is
if you have some set of actions
and some sum of rewards, instead
of just starting from one place
and evaluating the
gradient, we're
actually not going to
use the gradients at all.
And we'll just sample
a bunch of actions
and see what the values are.
So maybe we'll, for example,
a sample like this action.
We'll sample this action maybe
sample this one, maybe sample
this one, and so forth.
And the first version of
a sampling-based method
could just be to sample a
bunch of things in parallel
and then pick the best one.
This is basically just
called random sampling.
Sometimes, it
actually works better
than you think it might do.
And if we were to
do that, then we
would say that, OK, this
action has the highest.
And so maybe I will return
the corresponding action
for this value.
But you can also do something
a bit better than that even
without gradient
optimization, which
is that you could
look at these samples
and say, OK, it looks like--
maybe we have one additional
sample thing that we've--
maybe we've also sampled
something like this.
And in that case, one
thing that we could do
is instead of just
considering this one
and taking the best is we could
say, maybe we should sample
more over here, because these
are the ones that were the best.
And so we could
basically try to sample
more from the things
that were good.
So we could take
the ones that were
the best fit, some kind of
distribution over those,
like a simple distribution,
like a Gaussian.
Say that, OK.
These were the actions
that were the best.
So maybe we could fit
some Gaussian or sample
more from the actions
here and then do
another round of sampling from
that new distribution, where
now you're going to be sampling
more from this distribution.
You find that when you sample
for a second round, maybe
you get samples
that look like this.
And then that allows
you to hone in
on what a good action might be.
So on the slides,
instead of with actions
and maximizing rewards, I did it
with parameters and minimizing
some loss function.
But all the ideas are the same.
So for gradient descent,
we pick an initial value,
evaluate the gradient, move in
the direction of the gradient,
and repeat that process.
There's some underlying
function that we don't know.
And so we're trying to get to
the minimum of that function
using these gradients.
And likewise with sampling,
or another way to call this is
a 0th order optimization, we're
instead going to be sampling
points and trying to figure out
what a good value is just from
sampling.
And again, there
is some underlying
curve here that we don't know.
We can only evaluate samples or,
in the case of gradient descent,
the gradient at those samples.
One other nice thing about a
sampling-based optimization
is that it means that
you don't need gradients.
So it can apply to
discrete variables.
It can also apply to
scenarios where you maybe
know the reward function.
You have reward values.
But you don't know what the
gradient of the reward function
is.
If it's a discrete
reward function,
then getting the gradient
might be challenging.
And then to formalize this
kind of iterative sampling
process, where we're
trying to sample more
from the good actions,
one method for doing this
is cross-entropy method.
There's also a way to
do this with-- well,
if you have discrete actions,
you could also just--
well, there's somewhat
of a different process.
But you could also just
use random sampling
if your action space
is small enough.
So what cross-entropy
method, not
to be confused with
the cross-entropy loss,
is you sample from some
initial distribution.
This could be a
uniform distribution.
Then rank the samples
according to their loss.
Like, this would
be the best one.
This would be the second best,
the third best, fourth best,
and so forth.
And then take the best ones
like, these three ones.
And then fit a distribution,
like a Gaussian distribution,
to those best samples.
And then resample from
your distribution,
rerank, and repeat this process.
So it's basically like a very
simple sampling-based way
to try to get, in this
case, good actions.
It's like a general
optimization technique
that can be used for
any sort of objective.
Cool.
And then after this
process, eventually,
after you run some
number of iterations,
you'll return the
best sample that you
found in the last iteration.
The question is, can
you also use sampling
to approximate gradients?
Yes.
So there's something called
finite differences, where
if you don't have a
way to get gradients,
then you could try
to sample basically
points very close together and
then use that to basically look
at the difference between this
point and this point and use
that to estimate the gradient.
There's pros and cons to it.
But there's definitely
a valid approach.
Yeah.
The question is, why do I put
the quotes around the policy
here?
The reason is that we're not
learning a parametric policy.
We're not learning a neural
network to represent a policy.
And there's actually
an optimization process
underlying the policy here.
And so typically, it's
a policy in the sense
that it is mapping from a
state to an action or a state
to actually multiple
future actions.
But it's often not
referred to a policy
to differentiate
it from policies
that are more like
neural network,
like that are more compact.
Well, you can also have
a linear function that's
mapping states to actions.
The main thing is that
it's a process that's
like an iterative
optimization process
rather than some sort of
closed form, like here's
an action for a state.
So the question is, can we
talk a little bit about how
this policy is stored?
So the only thing that we
have learned at this point
is a dynamics model and
potentially a reward function.
And so the only thing
that we have stored
is the parameters of the
model and the parameters
of your reward model.
And then when you're actually
trying to figure out what to do
and what actions to take,
what policy to follow,
we don't have a neural
network that's telling us
what actions to take.
Instead, every single time
step, you're thinking, OK,
what's going to happen if
I do this, this, or this?
And then choosing
actions that you think
are good as a result of that
kind of thinking process.
You're using a lot more compute
as part of this process.
And you're doing
that in real time
as you're trying to figure
out what actions to take.
Yeah, we're not recording
what we're doing right now.
So the question is, when we
sample actions, can some of them
be out of distribution?
So yeah, when you select the
distribution to sample from,
your actions might be
out of distribution
compared to the data that
the model was trained on.
And we'll talk in the next
slide on how to deal with that.
So the question
is, because we're
doing so much
compute at test time,
if you've finished computing
and by the time you finish
computing, the
state has changed,
how do you account for that?
I don't know if I have
a great answer for you.
I think that, typically, when
people run this in practice,
they just try to make that
compute process as fast
as possible so that they don't
have to account for the change.
I guess one thing you can do is
you're kind of planning actually
a sequence of actions here.
And so if you can estimate how
long that computation took--
if it took like two time steps,
for example, then instead
of starting by executing
at, you could actually
start by executing at
plus 3 or at plus 2,
depending on how
[? that ?] one works.
And so that's kind of
accounting for the fact
that time has moved forward.
The downside there
is that at and at
plus 1 might be different from
what was actually executed.
And so you might be
in a different state
from where you thought
you ended up in.
And so that
introduces challenges.
And it's actually somewhat
of an open research problem
on how best to handle
that sort of thing,
especially if you're basically
asynchronously like running
this process.
And also, the world
is evolving as well.
So going back to doing
this with gradient descent
versus with samples,
there's pros and cons
to gradient-based
and sampling-based.
And this helps elucidate why
sampling-based actually can
be a good choice for planning.
So gradient descent
is very scalable even
to very high dimensions.
And it works well, especially
in overparameterized regimes,
when you have a big
neural network that's
representing a function
that may actually
have fewer free parameters.
The downside is that it
requires a nice optimization
landscape where your gradients
are fairly smooth rather
than not smooth, I guess.
With neural networks,
it ends up being--
especially because
neural networks
have high dimensional
parameter spaces
and are overparameterized,
the pros
end up heavily
outweighing the cons here.
Some of the upsides with
sampling-based approaches
is that it's really easy
to parallelize because you
can actually estimate
multiple samples
in parallel, whereas
gradient descent,
it inevitably has to be a
very sequential process, where
you compute one gradient and
then apply it and then compute
the next gradient and so forth.
And this parallelization
can actually, in some cases,
make it faster.
It doesn't require gradients
if you don't have them.
The downside is that it scales
poorly to high dimensions.
Because if you have a really
high dimensional space,
it's very hard to cover
that high dimensional space
with lots of different samples.
So in one dimensions,
something like this
can actually work
really, really well.
But if you can imagine, instead
of this being one-dimensional
or two-dimensional
or 10-dimensional,
you have to have your samples
cover that space well in order
to find a good optimum.
So specifically, what
the planning approach
would look like with a
sampling-based optimization is
you will still run some policy
and train some model, like we
did in the first two steps.
And we'll also be
choosing actions that
are trying to maximize rewards.
So essentially,
things are the same,
except the way that we do this
optimization problem is going
to change, where instead of
running gradient descent,
we could instead sample a
bunch of different actions,
imagine what will
happen in the future
and what rewards
we'll get, and then
potentially refine our
selection of actions
iteratively to then
get a good outcome.
And so in terms
of what this looks
like, if we use capital
A as shorthand to denote
this at to at plus H, then
version 1 is if we just
do one round of
sampling, then we'll
sample a large number of
possible action choices
we could take from
some distribution,
then choose the set of actions
that had the highest reward,
and then run those actions
in the environment.
The technical name for this is
often called random shooting
because you're kind of shooting
out different possible samples
of what could happen in the
future, imagining the future,
evaluating the reward, and then
just picking the one shot that
had the highest reward.
Now, the downside
and the thing that's
kind of unsatisfying
about this first algorithm
is that this distribution
may not be very good.
And so what we
could do is we could
use the cross-entropy method,
where we're iteratively
improving that
distribution, where we start
from some distribution,
maybe a uniform distribution,
evaluate, rank, and pick
the best samples that
have the highest
rewards and then
refit a new distribution
to those best samples
and repeat that process,
where we're then
going to be sampling from
that better distribution
and then evaluating those
samples and repeating.
If this is parallelized,
this process
actually can be quite fast.
If you have
low-dimensional actions,
it's actually also pretty
simple to implement.
But like we talked about,
it doesn't scale well
to high dimensions.
And so it's best if you have a
somewhat low-dimensional space
that you're considering.
This includes both H and
a because the optimization
that you're considering is
over this vector right here.
And the size of this is the
dimensionality of your action
space times the horizon.
Let's run through an example
for roughly how this would work.
So let's say that we are in this
simple, beautiful environment.
And you are trying
to maximize reward.
Maybe you're trying to
get to the highest point.
Because the highest point,
you get the nicest view.
So your reward is just like
the height of where you get to.
You run some policy.
You collect some data like this.
And maybe you learn that when
you train a model on this data,
that when you move right,
then you go higher.
Because generally,
when you move right,
the elevation became higher.
And then when you try to choose
actions according to your model,
then you're going to learn
that you should go right.
So you'll learn that
when you're actually
kind of finding actions
that maximize reward,
your set of actions
will be to go right.
And then you'll actually
execute those actions.
And you'll go right,
which is good for a bit.
You'll be maximizing
reward for a while.
And then at some point,
you'll fall off the cliff.
And that's not so good.
And this is because the
thing that we talked
about at the very
beginning, there's
this data distribution
mismatch where
the data that you
collected at the beginning
doesn't cover the
data that you are
taking with your final policy.
And so we have a
simple fix to this.
The simple fix is that when
we then execute actions
in our environment, we can then
add those actions to our data
set and refit our
model to that data set,
learn a more accurate model,
and repeat this process.
So then this is starting to
look a little bit more like
a reinforcement learning
algorithm because we're actually
iteratively collecting data,
fitting a better model--
in this case, a dynamics model--
sampling actions, choosing
actions to execute,
and running those actions
in the environment.
And so then when we do this, we
will then execute the actions
that we planned.
So we'll go off the cliff.
Then we'll learn that our model
will become more accurate.
We'll learn that if we
go right past this point,
we get a lot of
negative rewards.
Or we get a lot of very low
elevation, which corresponds
to negative rewards.
And then we'll be able to learn
a model that goes to the top
and stops.
Now, there is a number of
things that we could still
improve about this algorithm.
And let's talk about
a few of those.
So, so far, we've been
executing this set of actions
right here in the environment.
So we've been planning
out a sequence of actions,
executing them.
And so what that looks
like is we have our agent.
And our agent is like--
we're running H actions
in the environment--
so action at, at
plus 1, at plus 2,
and so forth in
some environment.
And we're executing
those actions
without actually having access
to the previous intermediate
states.
And one alternative
that you can consider
is something where
at each time, we're
going to be planning at to
at plus H. But we could also
have something where
we plan at to t plus H.
But we only actually execute
at in the environment.
And then we then get the
next state back in return.
And then we replan at the next
time step a new set of actions.
And so the difference
between these two things--
this is often what's called open
loop because you're not actually
using the feedback
from the environment,
the intermediate st's, when you
are executing future actions,
whereas this is often
called closed loop
because you're actually
kind of replanning
as you get new states.
So here's what that looks like.
Now, I'm curious, does anyone
have thoughts on scenarios
in which it might be bad
to be open loop like this,
where you're only planning based
off of st and not planning based
off of all of the future st's?
Yeah, so when the environment
is changing a lot.
So if the environment
changed in a way that
is different from what you
anticipated because you maybe
weren't able to predict
everything that would happen,
then you won't react
to those changes
when you act in
an open loop way.
And instead, if
you're closed loop
and you're reconsidering based
off of the latest states,
then you're able to actually
react to those changes
and, potentially in
some cases, actually
have a much, much better
policy, whereas in scenarios
where the world is a little
bit more deterministic,
then it can be OK to be a
little bit open loop at times.
But you usually never want
to have at be too large.
Otherwise, you're
executing two open loops.
Now, we talked about how we can
make planning closed loop, which
is instead of executing
the entire action sequence,
you just execute only
the first planned action.
So we're still going to
plan a sequence of actions
because we need to consider
not just the first action
but how all of our actions are
going to affect future rewards.
But then we'll execute
only the first one,
observe the resulting state.
And then we will then replan
an action sequence starting
at that new next state.
And then we can also,
like before, kind of also
add the data to our data set
and periodically refit our model
based off of the latest data.
This algorithm right
here is something called
model predictive control.
It's very, very common in
certain robotic systems,
very widely used.
It's also used in other kind
of simple control systems
as well, where you can model
lower dimensional systems.
It can be quite effective
for legged robots
as well, where you're
trying to learn models.
And you're able to plan
over the next couple seconds
to figure out what will
lead to good performance
over the next couple of seconds.
And this sort of replanning,
when you actually
are considering a new plan
at the next time step,
if something changes or if you
made a mistake, you slipped
or something, this
replanning allows
you to actually consider a
completely different course
of action and, for
example, correct for not
just for changing environments.
It can also actually
correct for model errors.
And so generally,
this sort of approach,
if your model is accurate in a
large part of the state space
but in some parts of the
state space, it's inaccurate,
this sort of approach
ends up actually
being a lot more robust to
those kinds of model errors.
Yeah, that's a good question.
So if there are
multiple correct paths,
the question is, in that
kind of multi-modality,
will that lead to oscillation
between those different paths?
It certainly can lead to that if
you're replanning all the time.
And you might start
going in one direction.
And then maybe say
like, oh, maybe I'll
go in a different direction.
Sometimes, you also won't
see that if the state kind of
indicates that you've clearly
committed to one direction.
So sometimes, you see it.
Sometimes, you don't.
The other way to accommodate
this and also actually address
computational
challenges is that you
can warm start your plan
for any given time step
to, basically, the plan
from the previous time step.
And so if you had
planned at to at plus H
and that the next time
step you are planning--
based off of st plus 1,
you're planning at plus 1
to t plus 1 plus H,
then what you can do
is you can actually
warm start this using
everything but the first time
step of this previous plan
and then randomly
initialize the last action.
And you'll already have
some kind of initial plan
that is sensible.
And so you don't have to run
as long of an optimization
procedure.
And it also helps you commit
to the previous action
in the previous plan.
Yeah.
Instead of randomly
initializing--
for example, in our
sampling-based thing,
you could--
either here or in a
sampling-based approach,
you could initialize close
to the previous plan.
You could also add some
noise or add some variance
to your sampling distribution so
that you're not only considering
that particular plan.
So replanning helps with
non-deterministic environments.
It also is really, really
useful for model errors.
It is also compute-intensive.
So warm starting can be helpful.
If you're actually replanning
it every single time step,
it means that every
single time step,
you're kind of reconsidering
what action to take.
And so it also can introduce
additional compute challenges
as well.
Sometimes, you have something
in the middle where you'll
have some planning horizon.
But then maybe you'll replan not
every one step but every three
steps or every 10
steps or something
like that, where
maybe your horizon is
something like 100 time steps.
So it's an interesting question.
So the question was like, as
you're learning and getting
more data, presumably your
model is going to get better.
And you have more
confidence in your model.
And so maybe insofar as this
is really useful for correcting
for model errors, you might be
able to replan less frequently
when you have a better model.
So that is certainly
very viable.
And usually, at
some point, you will
have some kind of final
model that you're using
after the learning process.
And you could use different
hyperparameters with regard
to replanning for
that final policy
versus during the
learning process.
And during the learning process,
it can also be valuable--
the model errors also help
you explore to some extent
because you're going
to be exploring
exactly the regions where
the model is inaccurate
because you'll be incentivized
to exploit any inaccuracies.
So the question is,
it seems like this
is an off-policy algorithm.
And does it make sense how
do you choose that policy?
So yes, this is an
off-policy algorithm.
We don't need to be using
data from our current policy.
You can actually use
a pretty broad policy.
And it makes sense to use a
pretty broad policy because then
you'll get a model that's
accurate in more places,
assuming that your
model is expressive
and can fit that broader
data distribution.
So far, we've covered
planning with models.
So we plan a
sequence of actions.
We can do this either with
gradient descent or sampling.
We then update the model
using data collected
through this planning process.
And we can replan to help
account for mistakes.
This is a pretty simple
way to use a learned model.
One of the things that's, I
think, really cool about this
is if you have a model
that's quite good,
you can actually plug
in different rewards
or different goals at
test time even and get
a policy that can follow--
for example, if you have a
model that's universally good
and you have a robot
that's trying to walk, then
with that same
exact model, you can
use this process at
test time and say,
I want you to run forwards.
I want you to walk backwards.
I want you to crouch.
And this kind of model
is quite task-agnostic.
The downside is that it's
compute-intensive at test time.
And so you need to
account for this.
And if you have an
expensive model,
an expensive planning
process, this kind
of planning at test time
might not be suitable.
And the last thing is we've
been talking about this
for short horizon problems.
This is not applicable
to long horizon problems
unless you have a
shaped reward function.
So if you have a shaped reward
function that is telling you
a lot about what a good state
is versus what a bad state is--
for example, maybe you have
an infinite horizon problem
that you want to
walk forward forever.
You want to learn a policy
that can walk forward forever.
But you have a very
dense reward function
that's like forward velocity.
Then you can plan
for a short horizon
in a way that approximates
the long horizon problem.
But if you have a long
horizon problem that
doesn't have a very
dense reward signal,
then this is not
a good approach.
And part of the reason for this
is the accuracy of the model.
Another part of
this is that it's
going to be expensive to be
planning out a very long horizon
sequence of actions
because you're not
learning a policy in this case.
Now, the question is, can we
train a policy using this model?
And the first option here
is you could actually
distill a planner's
actions into a policy.
So you could store these
actions and then train a policy
to match these actions.
This would address the
compute-intensive problem.
And this would make it a
lot cheaper because then you
just need to run a forward
pass through the neural network
to get your actions.
This doesn't address the
horizon problem, though,
because we're still going
to be using this procedure
to optimize for actions.
And then in terms
of using models
for longer horizon problems,
there's two main solutions.
The first solution is
that right now, we're
optimizing for a sum of
rewards from t to t plus H.
And if we want to optimize for
a longer horizon of rewards,
so far the way
that we would have
to do that is by optimizing over
a longer horizon of actions,
which gets higher and
higher dimensional.
But another thing
that you could do
is that if you have a value
function or an estimate
of a value function,
then you could actually
use that value function to help
this process, where instead
of trying to maximize the sum
of rewards for the next H time
steps, you could optimize
for the sum of rewards
for the next time steps plus
your estimate of the value
of the state that you end up at
after taking those H actions.
And so this would end
up with an algorithm
where you're learning both a
model and a value function.
And then you would be running
this planning process.
You'd be considering a
bunch of different actions
over some horizon and
then pass that horizon.
You're just asking
your value function,
is that a good state
or a bad state?
And so this is a valid
way to combine planning
with value-based RL in
order to select actions.
So the question is,
why use the model?
Why not just use a
Q-function, for example?
This is why I didn't want
to spend too much time
on this method, is that in this
case, you have to learn a value
function and a model.
You're learning a lot
of different things.
And there's a lot
of moving pieces.
There is still some
merit to using this.
And for example, if
you know the model,
then you're going
to get a better
estimate of future rewards
than your value function.
And so you can actually use
this to plan out future actions.
Like, in games, it's
actually really common
to do these rollouts
through your model
of the game to the extent that
it's computationally feasible
and then use your value
function just because it's
going to be more accurate.
It's going to give
you a better estimate
of how good your action is.
But it's only if you
have a really good model
or if it's practical and not too
difficult to learn a good model.
And then the other approach,
which I'm thinking--
we don't have too much time.
And so I think I might cover
this second approach on Friday
and then go through
the case study.
So let's talk about
this case study.
So this case study
is actually going
to be an example
of using planning
for dexterous manipulation.
And the reason why I want to
cover this case study briefly
is that in my mind,
it's actually still
one of the most impressive
robotics results
with a five-fingered hand.
And it also has some
pretty nice comparisons
that are elucidating
about what is
important for good performance
in model-based RL and planning.
So the way it
works is the states
are the position of the hand
and the position of objects.
This assumes that you know
the 3D position of an object,
which you can estimate with a
computer vision system or put
motion capture markers
on the objects,
whereas the hand position, you
can use sensors in the hand
itself in order to measure
the hand positions.
The action space is to
control a five-fingered hand.
It has 24 different joints
that you can control.
And the reward is to target some
kind of object trajectory, where
there's also some penalty
for dropping the object.
The model is going to be
actually pretty simple.
The model is going to be a
neural network with two hidden
layers of size 500.
But it's also going to train
an ensemble of neural networks.
And this is an
example that I wanted
to look at because this
kind of ensembling approach
can also help with model errors.
And the way this works is
instead of just training
one neural network, you'll
train three neural networks
with different random
initializations
and different kind of
mini batch sampling, just
with different random seeds.
And then if one model is
very optimistic about what
will happen, that can
be counterbalanced
by errors in other models.
And it essentially gives you
a way to deal with the fact
that models will have different
errors in different ways.
So you're not going to exploit
the errors in any one model.
And then the planner
is a modified version
of the cross-entropy method.
So it's going to be using
iterative resampling
of the actions.
And the modifications
are that it's
going to use this softer
reward weighted mean.
And it does some
sort of temporal
smoothing on the actions
to encourage and search
over actions that are taking
smoother trajectories.
But you can
basically think of it
as cross-entropy
method or this kind
of iterative sampling-based
optimization.
And then they alternate
between, in step 1,
collecting 30 trajectories
and updating the model.
So then in the
simulated experiments,
we are going to see a comparison
to some model free methods,
methods that are not
using a dynamics model.
We'll see [? soft ?] actor
critic and an algorithm
called natural policy gradient,
which is a policy gradient
method.
And then we'll also see
some model-based methods.
So the proposed
method is called PDDM.
We'll also see an
algorithm called
MBPO, a different kind
of planner called PETS,
and then also a method
that doesn't use ensembles
and doesn't use
iterative sampling.
And here are some
videos of what you're
able to do with this method.
So we're running planning in
the loop of actually execution.
And we see that
it's able to learn
how to rotate the
bounding balls in the hand
and also write digits
on this piece of paper.
And we see that if we plot the
kind of reward where higher
is better over the
number of data points
that are collected in
order to fit the model
or in the policy in the
case of model free methods,
we see that, first, for this
really complex task, only
the proposed method is able
to solve it because it's
really challenging.
And we also see that some of the
methods that, for example, don't
do iterative sampling,
that, for example, just do
random sampling,
shown in yellow,
get very poor performance
because you're not
able to get to a good
part of the distribution
and hone in on good actions.
And in the case of handwriting,
which is a little bit easier,
we see that some methods are
able to get good performance.
SAC and natural policy
gradient get high performance.
But they need far, far more data
than this model-based method,
which is shown in green.
And so the model-based method
is using maybe on the order
of 100,000 time steps of data,
whereas the model-free methods
are using half a
million time steps.
So it's a lot more efficient
than model-free methods.
It's also more performant than
other model-based methods.
We also see that the model
needs to be sufficiently large.
You also need this ensemble
for good performance.
And there's different trade-offs
with regard to the planning
horizon.
So you don't want
to plan for too
long into the future because
that's too high dimensional.
And then they also did it on
a real hand using the method
that we talked about.
Data efficiency is really
important for fragile hardware.
This robot hand is very fragile.
There actually is one at
Stanford in the Gates Building.
And I think all the students are
afraid to touch it because they
don't want to break it.
And then they have to figure out
how to fix it because it's also
really complicated.
And the success rate for
90-degree turns is actually
around 100% after just
four hours of data.
For 180-degree turns,
which is a bit harder,
the success rate is a bit lower.
But you're still able to
make significant performance
with four hours of data.
Also, they reset the system
when it dropped a ball using
another robot, like this setup.
That's it for today.
Next time, we'll cover the last
part about model-based RL and RL
with multiple tasks and goals.